A Guide to the Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse ca. 1935, 1959-1978 and 1992-2003
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse ca. 1935, 1959-1978 and 1992-2003
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10726-t
This addition to the papers of Alan Cheuse, ca. 1935, 1959-1978 and 1992-2003, consists of ca. 1,450 items (ca. 730 items in the correspondence series, 515 items in manuscripts, and 200 items in topical; 18 Hollinger boxes and one oversize folder).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were purchased by the University of Virginia Library on September 11, 2003, from Alan Cheuse, George Mason University.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Alan Cheuse, ca. 1935, 1959-1978 and 1992-2003, ca. 1,450 items (ca. 730 items in the correspondence series, 515 items in manuscripts, and 200 items in topical; 18 Hollinger boxes and one oversize folder) includes book reviews, short stories, articles, essays, and novels by Cheuse; two sets of proofs for Listening to the Page, date books; correspondence, postcards, and invitations; articles about Cheuse; and manuscripts by Nicholas Delbanco, Peter Najarian, and other authors. All materials stored on computer discs were printed and interfiled; the file date and disk number are written on the upper right corner of the first page of each document.
Correspondents include, from correspondence: Adler, Irving (2002 Dec 10); Aldridge, John W. (2000 Jun 11; 2000 Jul 14; 2000 Jul 24; 2000 Dec 7); Atlas, James (2000 Dec 4); Bacon, Charlotte (2000 Apr 13); Boyle, T. C. (2001 Sep 6); Byrd, Max (2000 May 23); Callanan, Liam (2001 Sep 9; 2002 n.d.); Canin, Ethan (2000 Jan 21); Cheney, Vice President Richard (2002 Jan 25); Ciabattari, Jane (2002 Apr 15); Clair, Maxine (2002 Jan 9); Collum, Danny Duncan (2001 Nov 27); Craig, Charmaine (2003 Feb 28); Cull, Mark E. (1999 Dec 6); Danticat, Edwidge (1999 Jun 19); Davis, W. Bowdoin (2001 Oct 15); DeBord, Matthew (2000 Jan 26); Delbanco, Nicholas and Elena (2001 May 25; 2001 Nov 1; 2002 Jan 23; 2002 Apr 3; 2002 Nov 29; n.d.); Evans, Elizabeth (2001 Jan 12); Fogarty, Robert (1999 Nov 30; 2000 Oct 18; 2001 Jan 20); Ford, Richard (2001 Nov 17); Fraser, Russell (2001 May 8; 2002 Feb 1); Free, Pamela (1999 Sep 15); Garrett, George (2002 Jul 11); Gerard, Philip (2002 Apr 11); Giardina, Anthony (2001 Mar 29); Gibbon, Maureen (2000 Apr 10); Giles, Molly (2000 Sep 29; 2001 Feb 6); Gililand, Gail (2002 Feb 28); Gold, Herbert (2001 Apr 27; 2001 May 10; 2001 May 21; 2002 Mar 25; 2002 May 13); Hall, Oakley (2001 Nov 30; 2002 Mar 6; 2002 Jul 8; 2003 Apr 2); Hall, Sands (2000 Oct 28; 2000 Nov 17); Hartman, Mary (2002 Oct 20); Henry, DeWitt (2001 Dec 9); Hirschfield, Jane (2000 Oct 9); Houston, James and Jeanne Wakatsuki (2000 Jan 25; 2001 Feb 1; 2001 Apr 4; 2001 Sep); Hower, Edward (2003 Jan 27); Jensen, Lisa (2001 Sep 11); Jin, Ha (1999 Oct 30); Koch, Stephen (2003 Apr, n.d.); Landis, J. D. (2000 Oct 24; 2001 Jun 30); Lesley, Craig (2000 Jan 29); Leviant, Curt (2000 Jan 1; 2000 Feb 17; 2003 Mar 31); Lopez, Barry (2000 Jan 15; 2001 Apr 1; 2002 Apr 14; 2002 May 23); Magnuson, James, Michener Center for Writers (2000 Jan 24); [Mailer?], Norman (2002 Nov 22); Marcus, Morton (2000 Apr 12); Meinke, Peter (2002 Apr 12); Melosh, Barbara (2000 Apr 12); Merrill, Christopher (1999 Aug 27); Morgan, Mike (2001 May 23); Najarian, Peter (2000 Jan 8; 2000 Aug 29; 2000 Sep 21; 2000 Oct 9; 2000 Dec 1; 2001 Apr 3; 2001 Dec 17; 2002 Mar 8); Nova, Craig (2002 Jan 30); Ochsner, Gina (2002 Apr 12); Peters, Daniel J. (2000 Feb 20); Pfarrer, Donald (1999 Sep 8); Pinsky, Robert (2001 May 22; 2002 Feb 3, n.d.); Pollan, Michael (2001 May 22); Prettyman, Barrett (2001 May 23); Prufer, Kevin (1999 Sep 13); Raffel, Dawn (2002 Nov 26); Rangel-Ribiero, Victor (2001 Jul 11; 2001 Jul 31; 2002 Feb 7); Salter, James (n.d.); Sandy, Stephen (2001 Jul 10; 2002 May 12; 2002 Jul 16); Schultz, Robert (2000 Mar 20); Shand, Rosa (2000 May 25); Shreve, Porter (2000 Sep 26); Shreve, Susan (1999 Nov 22; 2000 Jan 26); Silesky, Barry (2000 May 31); Smith, Janna (2001 May 21); Smith, William Jay (2000 Mar 11); Standiford, Les (1999 Nov 30; 2001 Jun 5); Stegner, Lynn (1999 Sep 13; 2000 Apr 3); Steinke, Darcey (2000 May 11); Stern, Kathryn (2000 Mar 6); Sward, Robert (2000 Feb 28); Taylor, Elizabeth, author (2000 Jun12); Thackara. James (1999 Aug 31); Thornton, Susan (2001 Jan 8); Vaz, Katherine (2000 Sep 19); Wagman, Diana (1999 Oct 5); White, Michael C. (1999 Dec 16); Wieland, Mitch (1999 Jun 17; 1999 Sep 1; 2000 Jan 7; 2001 Oct 10); Williams, Theresa (2002 Nov 25); Wyman, David S. (2000 Mar 3); Zabytko, Irene (2001 Feb 16); Zucker, Benjamin (2000 Sep 14; 2000 Oct 5).
From postcards: Delbanco, Nicholas and Elena (2001 May 22, n.d.); Ford, Richard (2000 Jun 3; 2000 Jun 29; 2002 Jun 10; 2002 Jul 6; 2002 Jul 17; 2002 Nov 1; 2003 Feb 6); Hall, Oakley (1999 Oct 13; 2001 Nov 16; 2002 Feb 5; 2002 Feb 20; 2002 Jun 1; 2003 Feb 9); James, Sonya (1999 Oct 4); Landis, J. D. (2001 May 22); Muske-Dukes, Carol (2002 Feb 13; 2002 Jul 1); Najarian, Peter (2002 Mar 21, n.d.); [Oates?], Joyce [Carol] (1999 Aug 13); Schulman, Audrey (2000 Sep).
Arrangement
This collection is organized in four series: Series I: Works by Alan Cheuse (Boxes 1-14); Series II: Works by Other Writers (Boxes 14-15); Series III: Correspondence (Boxes 15-17); and Series IV: Topical Files (Boxes 17-18).
Contents List
- Series I: Works by Alan Cheuse (Box 1-14)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1996], 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1997], 1-3 of 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1997], 4-6 of 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1996-1998], 1-4 of 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1996-1998], 5-9 of 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1999 Apr.-Jun.] (Box 3)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1999 Aug. 31], 1-5 of 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1999 Sep.], 6-7 of 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1999 Nov. 1-2] (Box 5)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1999 Nov.-2000], 1-3 of 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [1999 Nov.-2000], 4-7 of 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [2000 Apr.], 1-2 of 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [2000 Apr.], 3-4 of 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Biography of an Unknown Woman, draft [2000 May] (Box 7)
  - Book reviews by Alan Cheuse, authors' last names A-H n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Book reviews by Alan Cheuse, authors' last names I-M n.d. (Box 7)
  - Book reviews by Alan Cheuse, authors' last names N-Z n.d. (Box 7)
  - Book reviews by Alan Cheuse, more than one book n.d. (Box 7)
  - Essay "Ages of discovery" in The Chicago Tribune 2000 Oct. 8, draft and print from internet (Box 8)
  - Essay "An appetite as great as any other," drafts [1997 Apr. 25], n.d. (Box 8)
  - Essay "Border Jews," draft [1998] (Box 8)
  - Essay "Catching up with The Catcher in the Rye " in The Chicago Tribune, 2001 Jul. 8 (Box 8)
    draft and photocopy
  - Essay "Confessions of an ex-minimalist," drafts [2000], n.d. (Box 8)
  - Essay "The consolation of fiction," drafts [1996-1998] (Box 8)
  - Essay "e-browsing" in Land's End Catalogue 2000 (Box 8)
    photocopy
  - Essay "An elbow of land" in Preservation Magazine, drafts [2001] (Box 8)
  - Essay "Entre los ninos de escuela-Among school children," drafts [1999] (Box 8)
  - Essay "Finding a story, or using the whole pig," proof [2000] (Box 8)
  - Essay "Georgia O'Keefe's adobe" in The New York Times Travel Section 1998 Nov. 8 (Box 8)
    draft and print from internet
  - Essay "Little America" in Blue Cathedral, proof 1999 (Box 8)
  - Essay "It's a sweetheart" in Andre Dubus Tributes 2001 (Box 8)
  - Essay "Literary second acts in American lives" in The New York Times 2001 May 21 (Box 8)
  - Essays-miscellaneous 1997-2001, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Essay "Of the making of books," drafts [1999], n.d. (Box 8)
  - Essay "On the contemporary" [1998 Aug. 30?] (Box 8)
  - Essay "One more time: Rereading books" in The Chicago Tribune 2000 Aug. 6 (Box 8)
  - Essay "Port of entry: A fantasia on border themes" in San Diego Weekly Reader 1998 Jun. 11 (Box 8)
    drafts and photocopy
  - Essay "Some enchanted island" in Gourmet Magazine, proof 2002 Nov. (Oversize OS)
  - Essay "Present father," drafts [1996-1998] (Box 9)
  - Essay "Provide, provide" in San Diego Weekly Reader 2000 Jun. 1 (Box 9)
  - Essay "Reflections on Steinbeck" in John Steinbeck: Centennial Reflections by American Writers, proof 2002 (Box 9)
  - Essay "Some enchanted island" in Gourmet Magazine 2002 (Box 9)
  - Essay "Tacos and manna" in Writing Creative Nonfiction, proof 2000 (Box 9)
  - Essay "Traces of light: Paradoxes of pictorial fiction and narrative painting" [in The Antioch Review Summer 1997] [1996-1997] (Box 9)
  - Essay "Truth as fiction, or, The tail of the monstrous peacock," drafts [2000] (Box 9)
  - Essay "Underground writer, the work of Harold Humes" in Rediscoveries II n.d. (Box 9)
  - Essay "Where is she going? Where has she been?: Elizabeth Tallent's 'No one's a mystery' and the mysteries of initiation," drafts [1996-2000?] (Box 9)
  - Essay "Writing it down for James" in The Antioch Review 2001
    print from internet
  - Essay "The Year in Literature: USA" in Encyclopedia Britannica, drafts and proofs 1996-2001 (Box 9)
  - Listening to the Page by Cheuse, unbound proof 2001 Jan., 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Listening to the Page, unbound proof 2001 Feb., 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Listening to the Page, reviews of 2000 Dec. 30-2002 (Box 10)
  - On Earth as it is, draft [1995], 3 folders (Box 10)
  - On Earth as it is, draft [1996], 1 of 3 folders (Box 10)
  - On Earth as it is, draft [1996], 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Rowing in Eden [1994], 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Rowing in Eden [1996], 1 of 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Rowing in Eden [1996], 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Short story "A brief Washington-Mount Vernon chronology, followed by an aborted picnic at the Holocaust Museum," drafts [1999-2000]. n.d. (Box 12)
  - Short story, "Care," drafts [2000-2001] (Box 12)
  - Short story, "Care," draft and proof 2001 (Box 12)
  - Short story, "Compatibility," drafts [2000] (Box 12)
  - Short story, "Days given over to travel," draft [2003?] (Box 12)
  - Short story, "The distinction between twilight and crepuscule," draft and proof [2000] (Box 12)
  - Short story, "The Exorcism," drafts [2000] (Box 13)
  - Short story, "The fires," draft and proof 1999 (Box 13)
  - Short story, "Flutter," drafts and proof [1997]-2000 (Box 13)
  - Short story, "Horse sacrifice and the shaman's ascent to the sky" by Cheuse, draft [2001] (Box 13)
  - Short story, "Las Coronadas" by Cheuse, drafts 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Short story, "O body swayed" by Cheuse, drafts [1996-2000], n.d. (Box 13)
  - Short story, "Revels" by Cheuse, draft [2000] (Box 13)
  - You don't know where I'm going by Cheuse [1999] (Box 13)
  - You don't know where I'm going by Cheuse [2000], 2 folders (Box 14)
- Series II: Works by other writers (Box 14-15)
  - Articles "Unchain my heart" and "California, always on the brink" by James Houston 1999-2000 (Box 14)
    photocopies
  - The Countess of Stanlein Restored by Nicholas Delbanco, 2001 (Box 14)
  - Duchamp: Domestic patterns, covers, and threads by W. Bowdoin Davis, Jr. with preface by Alan Cheuse, bound page proof 2001 Aug. 27 (Box 14)
  - Essays, "A Francophile goes to Reno to look for Paris" and "King of the Cleveland beatniks" by Herbert Gold 1998, 2000 (Box 14)
  - Essays on Wilson Harris by Joyce Sparer Adler, manuscript 2002 Dec. 10 (Box 14)
  - "Henri Matisse, 1908, 1910, and 1912: New evidence of life" by John Canman in Modern Art and America: Alfred Steiglitz and his New York Galleries, proof 2001 (Box 14)
  - Manuscripts-miscellaneous, not by Cheuse n.d. (Box 14)
  - "A place on the map, a place in the mind: James D. Houston's Doyle Trilogy" by Andrew Wingfield in Western American Literature 34, no. 2 1999 (Folder 14)
  - Short stories: "Amsterdam," "Honolulu," "The quake," "The movements" by Peter Najarian, drafts 2001-2002 (Box 14)
  - "Alan Cheuse" by Jay Boyer in The Dictionary of Literary Biography, proof 2001 (Box 15)
  - "A conversation: Alan Cheuse and Andrew Wingfield" in Pleiades, n.d. (Box 15)
    proof and photocopy
- Series III: Correspondence (Box 15-17)
  - Correspondence-from Alan Cheuse to his parents 1959-1978, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Correspondence-from Alan Cheuse 1996-2002, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Correspondence 1998-2000, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - Correspondence 2001-2002, 6 folders (Box 16)
  - Correspondence 2003, n.d., 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Correspondence-Invitations 1999-2002, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Correspondence-Postcards 1992-2003, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Correspondence-Valentines n.d. (Box 17)
- Series IV: Topical (Box 17-18)
  - Calendar, made by Emma Cheuse, illustrated with family photographs 2000 (Oversize OS)
  - Curriculum vitae and activity reports [1997-2000] (Box 17)
  - Broadside for "Carrying on the Tradition" a talk given by Cheuse at the Chantilly, Virginia regional library n.d. (Oversize OS)
  - Datebooks 1999-2002 (Box 17)
  - "The light on Alan Cheuse, a dialogue" an interview by Neila C. Seshachari in Weber Studies [1990], photocopy (Box 17)
  - Newsclippings about Alan Cheuse 1955-57, 1992-2003 (Box 17)
  - Newsclippings concerning Perth Amboy, NY; James Houston; Norman Mailer, other 1999-2001 (Box 17)
  - Notebook [for "Crossing the Border"] n.d. (Box 17)
  - Notes, outlines 1993-1998, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Kris O'Shee 1996-2002 (Box 17)
  - Photographs n.d. (Box 18)
  - Photographs-Mother's photo album ca. 1935 (Box 18)
  - Programs and tickets 1959, 1999-2001 (Box 18)
  - Programs that mention Cheuse 1999-2002 (Box 18)
  - The Sound of Writing -scripts [1994-1995] (Box 18)
  - Speeches [1997]-2002, n.d. (Box 18)
  - Teaching materials and/or George Mason University 1999-2000, n.d. (Box 18)